part 3 chapter 2.
He was lying on something that felt like a camp bed, except that it was higher off
the ground and that he was fixed down in some way so that he could not move
lights that seemed stronger than usual was falling on his face.
O'Brien was standing at his side, looking down at him intently.
At the other side of him stood a man in a white coat, holding a hypodermic syringe.
Even after his eyes were open he took in his surroundings only gradually.
He had the impression of swimming up into this room from some quite different
world, a sort of underwater world far beneath it.
How long he had been down there he did not know.
Since the moment when they arrested him he had not seen darkness or daylight.
Besides, his memories were not continuous.
There had been times when consciousness, even the sort of consciousness that one
has in sleep, had stopped dead and started again after a blank interval.
But whether the intervals were of days or weeks or only seconds, there was no way of knowing.
With that first blow on the elbow the nightmare had started.
Later he was to realize that all that then happened was merely a preliminary, a
routine interrogation to which nearly all prisoners were subjected.
There was a long range of crimes— —espionage, sabotage and the like— —to which
everyone had to confess as a matter of course.
The confession was a formality, though the torture was real.
How many times he had been beaten, how long the beatings had continued, he could not remember.
Always there were five or six men in black uniforms at him simultaneously.
Sometimes it was fists, sometimes it was truncheons, sometimes it was steel rods,
sometimes it was boots.
There were times when he rolled about the floor, as shameless as an animal,
writhing his body this way into that in an endless, hopeless effort to dodge the
kicks, and simply inviting more and yet more kicks, in his ribs, in his belly, on
his elbows, on his shins, in his groin, in his testicles, on the bone at the base of
his spine.
There were times when it went on and on until the cruel, wicked, unforgivable
thing seemed to him not that the gods continued to beat him but that he could
not force himself into losing consciousness.
There were times when his nerve so forsook him that he began shouting for
mercy even before the beating began, when the mere sight of a fist drawn back for
a blow was enough to make him pour forth a confession of real and imaginary crimes.
There were other times when he started out with the resolve of confessing nothing,
when every word had to be forced out of him between gasps of pain, and there were
times when he feebly tried to compromise, when he said to himself:
'I will confess, but not yet. I must hold out till the pain becomes unbearable.
Three more kicks, two more kicks, and then I will tell them what they want.'
Sometimes he was beaten till he could hardly stand, then flung like a sack of
potatoes onto the stone floor of a cell, left to recuperate for a few hours, and
then taken out and beaten again.
There were also longer periods of recovery.
He remembered the dimly, because they were spent chiefly in sleep or stupa
He remembered a cell with a plank bed, a sort of shelf sticking out from the wall,
and a tin wash basin and meals of hot soup and bread and sometimes coffee.
He remembered a surly barber arriving to scrape his chin and crop his hair, and a
business-like unsympathetic men in white coats feeling his pulse, tapping his
reflexes, turning up his eyelids, running harsh fingers over him in search for
broken bones, and shooting needles into his arm to make him sleep.
The beatings grew less frequent, and became mainly a threat, a horror to which
he could be sent back at any moment when his answers were unsatisfactory.
His questioners now were not ruffians in black uniforms but Party intellectuals,
little rotunda men with quick movements and flashing spectacles, who worked on
him in relays over periods which lasted— —he thought, he could not be sure 10 or 12
hours at a stretch.
These other questioners saw to it that the team was in constant slight pain, but
it was not chiefly pain that they relied on.
They slapped his face rung his ears, pulled his hair, made him stand on one
leg, refused him leave to urinate strong glaring lights in his face until his
eyes ran with water; but the aim of this was simply to humiliate him and destroy
his power of arguing and reasoning.
Their real weapon was the merciless questioning that went on and on, hour
after hour, tripping him up, laying traps for him, twisting everything that he said,
convicting him at every step of lies and self-contradiction until he began
weeping as much from shame as from nervous fatigue.
Sometimes he would reap half a dozen times in a single session.
Most of the time they screamed abuse at him and threatened at every hesitation
to deliver him over to the guards again; but sometimes they would suddenly change
their tune, call him comrade, appeal to him in the name of insock and Big
Brother, and ask him sorrowfully whether even now he had not enough loyalty to
the Party left to make him wish to undo the evil he had done.
When his nerves were in rags after hours of questioning, even this appeal could
reduce him to sniveling tears.
In the end of the nagging voices broke him down more completely than the boots
and fists of the guards. He became simply a mouse that uttered, a hand that signed,
whatever was demanded of him.
His sole concern was to find out what they wanted him to confess, and then
confess it quickly, before the bullying started anew. He confessed to the
assassination of eminent Party members, the distribution of seditious pamphlets,
embezzlement of public funds, sale of military secrets, sabotage of every kind.
He confessed that he had been a spy in the pay of the East Asian government as
far back as 1968..
He confessed that he was a religious believer and admirer of capitalism and a
sexual pervert. He confessed that he had murdered his wife, although he knew, and
his questioners must have known, that his wife was still alive.
He confessed that for years he had been in personal touch with Goldstone and had
been a member of an underground organization which had included almost
every human being he had ever known. It was easier to confess everything and
implicate everybody.
Besides, in a sense it was all true. It was true that he had been the enemy of
the Party, and in the eyes of the Party there was no distinction between the
thought and the deed. There were also memories of another kind.
They stood out in his mind disconnected he liked pictures with blackness all around them.
He was in a self which might have been either dark or light, because he could
see nothing except a pair of eyes.
Near at hand some kind of instrument was ticking slowly and regularly.
The eyes grew larger and more luminous.
Suddenly he floated out of his seat, dived into the eyes and was swallowed up.
He was strapped into a chair surrounded by dials, under dazzling lights. A man in
a white coat was reading the dials. There was a trap of heavy boots outside. The
door clanged The wax faced officer marched in, followed by two guards.
'Room 101,' said the officer.
The man in the white coat did not turn around He did not look at Winston either;
he was looking only at the dials.
He was rolling down a mighty corridor, a kilometer wide, full of glorious, golden
light, roaring with laughter and shouting out confessions at the top of his voice.
He was confessing everything, even the things he had succeeded in holding back
under the torture.
He was relating the entire history of his life to an audience who knew it already.
With him with the gods the other question is the men in white coats,
O'Brien, Julia, Mr Charrington, all rolling down the corridor together and shouting
with laughter. Some dreadful thing which had land embedded in the future had
somehow been skipped over and had not happened.
Everything was all right, there was no more pain, the last detail of his life
was laid bare, understood, forgiven.
He was starting up from the plank bed in the half certainty that he had heard O'Brien's voice.
All through his interrogation, although he had never seen him, he had had the
feeling that O'Brien was at his elbow, just out of sight.
It was O'Brien who was directing everything. It was he who set the guards
onto Winston and who prevented them from killing him.
It was he who decided when Winston should scream with pain, when he should
have a respite, when he should be fed, when he should sleep, when the drugs
should be pumped into his arm.
It was he who asked the questions and suggested the answers.
He was the tormentor, he was the protector, he was the inquisitor, he was the friend.
And once— —Winston could not remember whether it was in drug to sleep, or in
normal sleep, or even in a moment of wakefulness— —a voice murmured in his ear:
'Don't worry, Winston you're in my keeping.
For seven years I have watched over you.
Now the Turning Point has come. I shall save you, I shall make you perfect.'
He was not sure whether it was O'Brien's voice; but it was the same voice that had
said to him, 'We shall meet in the place where there is no darkness,' in that other
dream, seven years ago.
He did not remember any ending to his interrogation.
There was a period of blackness and then the cell, or room, in which he now was had
gradually materialized around him.
He was almost flat on his back, and unable to move.
His body was held down at every essential point. Even the back of his
head was gripped in some manner.
.O'Brien was looking down at him gravely and rather sadly.
His face, seen from below, looked coarse and worn, with pouches under the eyes and
tired lines from nose to chin.
He was older than Winston had thought him; he was perhaps 48 or 50. Under his
hand there was a dial with a lever on top and figures running around the face.
'I told you,' said O'Brien, 'that if we met again it would be here.'
'Yes,' said Winston.
Without any warning except a slight movement of O'Brien's hand, a wave of pain flooded his body.
It was a frightening pain, because he could not see what was happening, and he
had the feeling that some mortal injury was being done to him.
He did not know whether the thing was really happening, or whether the effect
was electrically produced; but his body was being wrenched out of shape, the
joints were being slowly torn apart.
Although the pain had brought the sweat out on his forehead, the worst of all was
the fear that his backbone was about to snap.
He set his teeth and breathed hard through his nose, trying to keep silent as long as possible.
'You are afraid,' said O'Brien, watching his face, 'that in another moment something is
going to break.
Your special fear is that it will be your backbone. You have a vivid mental
picture of the vertebrae snapping apart and the spinal fluid dripping out of them.
That is what you're thinking, is it not, Winston?'
Winston did not answer.
O'Brien drew back the lever on the dial.
The wave of pain receded almost as quickly as it had come.
'That was 40 said O'Brien. 'You can see that the numbers on this dial run up to
a hundred.
Will you please remember, throughout our conversation, that I have it in my power
to inflict pain on you at any moment and to whatever degree I choose.
If you tell me any lies, or attempt to prevaricate in any way, or even fall
below your usual level of intelligence, you will cry out with pain, instantly. Do
you understand that?'
'Yes,' said Winston.
O'Brien's manner became less severe. He resettled his spectacles thoughtfully,
and took a pace or two up and down.
When he spoke his voice was gentle and patient. He had the heir of a doctor, a
teacher, even a priest, anxious to explain and persuade rather than to punish.
'I am taking trouble with you, Winston,' he said, 'because you are worth trouble.
You know perfectly well what is the matter with you. You have known it for
years, though you have fought against the knowledge.
You were mentally deranged. You suffer from a defective memory. You are unable
to remember real events, and you persuade yourself that you remember other events
which never happened.
Fortunately it is curable. You have never cured yourself of it, because you did not choose to.
There was a small effort of the will that you were not ready to make.
Even now, I am well aware, you are clinging to your disease under the
impression that it is a virtue.
Now we will take an example. At this moment, which power is Oceania at war with?'
'When I was arrested, Oceania was at war with East Asia With East Asia Good.
And Oceania has always been at war with East Asia has it not?'
Winston drew in his breath. He opened his mouth to speak and then did not speak. He
could not take his eyes away from the dial.
'The truth, please, Winston. Your truth. Tell me what you think you remember.'
'I remember that until only a week before I was arrested, we were not at war with
East Asia at all. We were in alliance with them. The war was against Eurasia.
That had lasted for four years. Before that that Brian stopped him with the movement
of the hand.
'Another example,' he said.
'Some years ago you had a very serious delusion indeed.
You believed that three men, three one-time Party members named Jones,
Aaronson and Rutherford— —men who were executed for treachery and sabotage
after making the fullest possible confession— —were not guilty of the crimes they were
charged with.
You believed that you had seen unmistakable documentary evidence
proving that their confessions were false.
There was a certain photograph about which you had a hallucination.
You believe that you actually held it in your hands. It was a photograph something like this.'
An oblong slip of newspaper had appeared between O'Brien's fingers. For perhaps
five seconds it was within the angle of Winston's vision.
It was a photograph, and there was no question of its identity.
It was the photograph.
It was another copy of the photograph of Jones, Aaronson and Rutherford at the
Party function in New York, which he had chanced upon 11 years ago and promptly destroyed.
For only an instant it was before his eyes, then it was out of sight again. But
he had seen it, unquestionably he had seen it! He made a desperate agonizing
effort to wrench the top half of his body free. It was impossible to move so
much as a centimeter in any direction.
For the moment he had even forgotten the dial.
All he wanted was to hold the photograph in his fingers again, or at least to see it.
'It exists!' he cried.
'No,' said O'Brien.
He stepped across the room. There was a memory hole in the opposite wall. O'Brien
lifted the grating. Unseen, the frail slip of paper was whirling away on the
current of warm air; it was vanishing in a flash of flame.
O'Brien turned away from the wall.
'Ashes,' he said. 'Not even identifiable ashes. Dust. It does not exist.
It never existed.'
'But it did exist! It does exist! It exists in memory. I remember it. You remember it.'
'I do not remember it,' said O'Brien.
Winston's heart sank. That was double think He had a feeling of deadly helplessness.
If you could have been certain that O'Brien was lying, it would not have
seemed to matter. But it was perfectly possible that O'Brien had really
forgotten the photograph.
And if so, then already he would have forgotten his denial of remembering it,
and forgotten the act of forgetting.
How could one be sure that it was simple trickery? Perhaps that lunatic
dislocation in the mind could really happen: that was the thoughts that defeated him.
O'Brien was looking down at him speculatively. More than ever he had the
air of a teacher taking pains with a wayward but promising child.
'There is a Party slogan dealing with the control of the past,' he said. 'Repeat it, if
you please.'
'"Who controls the past controls the future: who controls the present controls
the past,"' repeated Winston obediently. '"Who controls the present controls the past,"'
said O'Brien, nodding his head with slow approval.
'Is it your opinion, Winston, that the past has real existence?'
Again the feeling of helplessness descended upon Winston. His eyes splitted towards the dial.
He not only did not know whether 'yes' or 'no' was the answer that would save him
from pain; he did not even know which answer he believed to be the true one.
O'Brien smiled faintly.'
.'You are no metaphysician, Winston,' he said.
'Until this moment you had never considered what is meant by existence.
I will put it more precisely.
Does the past exist concretely, in space?
Is there somewhere or rather a place, a world of solid objects, where the past is
still happening?'
'No.'
'Then where does the past exist, if at all?'
'In records. It is written down.'
'In records. And— 'In the mind. In human memories.'
'In memory. Very well, then. We, the Party, control all records, and we control all
memories. Then we control the past, do we not?'
'But how can you stop people remembering things?' cried Winston, again momentarily
for getting the dial. 'It is involuntary.
It is outside oneself. How can you control memory? You have not controlled mine!'
O'Brien's Manor grew stern again. He laid his hand on the dial.
'On the contrary,' he said, 'you have not controlled it. That is what has brought you here
because you have failed in humility, in self-discipline. You would not make the
act of submission which is the price of sanity. You prefer to be a lunatic, a
minority of one.
Only the disciplined mind can see reality, Winston.
You believe that reality is something objective, external, existing in its own right.
You also believe that the nature of reality is self-evident
When you delude yourself into thinking that you see something, you assume that
everyone else sees the same thing as you.
But I tell you, Winston, that reality is not external. Reality exists in the human
mind, and nowhere else.
Not in the individual mind, which can make mistakes, and in any case soon perishes:
only in the mind of the Party, which is collective and immortal.
Whatever the Party holds to be the truth, is truth. It is impossible to see reality
accepted by looking through the eyes of the Party.
That is the fact that you have got to relearn Winston.
It needs an act of self-destruction and effort of the will. You must humble
yourself before you can become sane.'
He paused for a few moments, as though to allow what he had been saying to sink in.
'Do you remember,' he went on, 'writing in your diary, "Freedom is the freedom to say
that two plus two make four"?'
'Yes,' said Winston.
O'Brien held up his left hand it's back towards Winston, with the thumb hidden
and the four fingers extended.
'How many fingers am I holding up, Winston?'
'Four.'
'And if the Party says that it is not four but five— —then how many?'
The word ended in a gasp of pain.
The needle of the dial had shot up to 55. The sweat had sprung out all over
Winston's body. The air tore into his lungs and issued again in deep groans
which even by clenching his teeth he could not stop.
O'Brien watched him, the four fingers still extended. He drew back the lever.
This time the pain was only slightly eased.
'How many fingers, Winston?' 'Four.'
The needle went up to 60. How many fingers, Winston?'
'Four! Four! What else can I say? Four!'
The needle must have risen again, but he did not look at it. The heavy Stone face
and the four fingers filled his vision.
The fingers stood up before his eyes like pillars, enormous, blurry and seeming
to vibrate, but unmistakably for How many fingers, Winston?'
'Four! Stop it, stop it! How can you go on?
Four! Four!'
'How many fingers, Winston?'
'Five! Five! Five!'
'No, Winston, that is no use. You are lying.
You still think there are four. How many fingers, please?'
'Four! Five! Four! Anything you like. Only stop it, stop the pain!'
Abruptly he was sitting up with her Brand's arm around his shoulders.
He had perhaps lost consciousness for a few seconds.
The bonds that had held his body down were loosened. He felt very cold, he was
shaking uncontrollably, his teeth were chattering, the tears were rolling down his cheeks.
For a moment he clung to a brine like a baby, curiously comforted by the heavy
arm around his shoulders.
He had the feeling that O'Brien was his protector, that the pain was something
that came from outside, from some other source, and that it was O'Brien who would
save him from it.
'You are a slow learner, Winston,' said O'Brien gently.
'How can I help it?' he blubbard How can I
help seeing what is in front of my eyes?
Two and two are four.'
'Sometimes, Winston.
Sometimes they are five. Sometimes they're three. Sometimes they're all of
them at once. You must try harder. It is not easy to become sane.'
He laid Winston down on the bed. The grip of his limbs tightened again, but the
pain had ebbed away and the trembling had stopped, leaving him merely weak and cold.
O'Brien motioned with his head to the man in the white coat, who had stored
immobile throughout the proceedings.
The man in the white coat bent down and looked closely into Winston's eyes, felt
his pulse, laid an ear against his chest, tapped here and there; then he nodded through Orion
Again,' said O'Brien The pain flowed into Winston's body. The
needle must be at 70 75 He had shut his eyes this time. He knew that the fingers
were still there, and still four. All that mattered was somehow to stay alive until
the spasm was over.
He had ceased to notice whether he was crying out or not.
The pain lessened again. He opened his eyes.
O'Brien had drawn back the lever.
'How many fingers, Winston?'
'Four. I suppose there are four. I would see five if I could I'm trying to see five.'
'Which do you wish: to persuade me that you see five, or really to see them?'
'Really to see them.'
'Again,' said O'Brien.
Perhaps the needle was 80 90. weinstead could not intermittently remember why
the pain was happening. Behind his screwed up eyelids a Forester fingers
seemed to be moving in a sort of dance, weaving in and out, disappearing behind
one another and reappearing again.
He was trying to counter them, he could not remember why. He knew only that it
was impossible to count them, and that this was somehow due to the mysterious
identity between five and four.
The pain died down again.
When he opened his eyes it was to find that he was still seeing the same thing.
Innumerable fingers, like moving trees, were still streaming past in either
direction, crossing and re-crossing He shut his eyes again.
'How many fingers am I holding up, Winston?'
'I don't know.
I don't know. You will kill me if you do that again. Four, five, six— —in all honesty
I don't know.'
'Better,' said O'Brien.
A needle slid into Winston's arm. Almost in the same instant a blissful, healing
warmth spread all through his body.
The pain was already half forgotten He opened his eyes and looked up
gratefully at O'Brien. At the site of the heavy, lined face, so ugly and so
intelligent, his heart seemed to turn over.
If he could have moved he would have stretched out a hand and laid it on O'Brien's arm.
He had never loved him so deeply as at this moment, and not merely because he had stopped
the pain. The old feeling, that at bottom it did not matter whether O'Brien was a
friend or an enemy, had come back.
O'Brien was a person who could be talked to. Perhaps one did not want to be loved
so much as to be understood. O'Brien had tortured him to the edge of lunacy, and
in a little while, it was certain, he would send him to his death.
It made no difference. In some sense that went deeper than friendship, they were intimates:
somewhere or other, although the actual words might never be spoken, there was a
place where they could meet and talk.
O'Brien was looking down at him with an expression which suggested that the same
thought might be in his own mind.
When he spoke it was in an easy, conversational tone.
'Do you know where you are, Winston?' he said.
'I don't know. I can guess. In the Ministry of Love.'
'Do you know how long you have been here?'
'I don't know. Days, weeks, months— —I think it is months.'
'And why do you imagine that we bring people to this place?'
'To make them confess.'
'No, that is not the reason. Try again.'
'To punish them.'
'No!' exclaimed a bran His voice had changed extraordinarily, and his face had
suddenly become both stern and animated.
'No! Not merely to extract your confession not to punish you.
Shall I tell you why we have brought you here? To cure you! To make you sane! Will
you understand, Winston, that no one whom we bring to this place ever leaves our
hands uncured? We are not interested in those stupid crimes that you have committed.
The Party is not interested in the overt act: the thought is all we care about.
We do not merely destroy our enemies, we change them.
Do you understand what I mean by that?'
He was bending over Winston. His face looked enormous because of its nearness,
and hideously ugly because it was seen from below.
Moreover it was filled with a sort of exaltation, a lunatic intensity.
Again Winston's heart shrank. If it had been possible he would have cowered
deeper into the bed. He felt certain that O'Brien was about to twist the dial out
of sheer wantedness At this moment, however, O'Brien turned
away. He took a pace or two up and down.
Then he continued less vehemently: 'The first thing for you to understand is
that in this place there are no martyrdoms. You have rid of the religious
persecutions of the past. In the Middle Ages there was the Inquisition. It was a
failure. It set out to eradicate heresy, and ended by perpetuating it. For every
heretic it burnt at the stake, thousands of others rose up. Why was that?
Because the Inquisition killed its enemies in the open, and killed them
while they were still unrepented in fact, it killed them because they were unrepentant.
Men were dying because they would not abandon their true beliefs. Naturally all
the glory belonged to the victim and all the shame to the Inquisitor who burnt him.
Later, in the 20th century, there were totalitarians, as they were called.
There were the German Nazis and the Russian Communists. The Russians
persecuted heresy more cruelly than the Inquisition had done.
And they imagined that they had learned from the mistakes of the past;
they knew, at any rate, that one must not make matters Before they exposed their victims to
public trial, they deliberately set themselves to destroy their dignity. They
wore them down by torture and solitude until they were despicable, cringing riches
confessing whatever was put into their mouths, covering themselves with abuse,
accusing and sheltering behind one another, whimpering for mercy.
And yet after only a few years the same thing had happened ever again. The dead
men had to become martyrs and their degradation was forgotten. Once again, why
was it? In the first place, because the confessions that they had made were
obviously extorted and untrue. We do not make mistakes of that kind.
All the confessions that are added here are true.
We make them true. And above all we do not allow the dead to rise up against us.
You must stop imagining that posterity will vindicate you, Winston.
Posterity will never hear of you. You will be lifted clean out from the stream
of history. We shall turn you into gas and pour you into the stratosphere.
Nothing will remain of you; not a name in a register, not a memory in a living
brain. You will be annihilated in the past as well as in the future. You will
never have existed and why bother to torture me? thought Winston, with a momentary bitterness.
O'Brien checked his step as though Winston had uttered the thought aloud.
His large ugly face came nearer, with the eyes a little narrowed.
'You were thinking,' he said, 'that since we intend to destroy you utterly, so that
nothing that you say or do can make the smallest difference—
—in that case, why do we go to the trouble of interrogating you first?
That is what you were thinking, was it not?'
'Yes,' said Winston.
O'Brien smiled slightly.
'You were a flaw in the pattern, Winston.
You were a stain that must be wiped out.
Did I not tell you just now that we are different from the persecutors of the past?
We are not content with negative obedience, nor even with the most abject submission.
When finally you surrender to us, it must be of your own free will.
We do not destroy the heretic because he resists us: so long as he resists us we
never destroy him. We convert him, we capture his inner mind, we reshape him. We
burn all evil and all the illusion out of him; we bring him over to our side, not
in appearance, but genuinely, heart and soul.
We make him one of ourselves before we kill him. It is intolerable to us that an
erroneous thought should exist anywhere in the world, however secret and
powerless it may be. Even in the instant of death we cannot permit any deviation.
In the old days the heretic walked to the stakes still a heretic, proclaiming
his heresy exalting in it.
Even the victim of the Russian purges could carry rebellion locked up in his
skull as he walked down the passage waiting for the bullet.
But we make the brain perfect before we blow it out. The command of the old
despotisms was "Thou shalt not".
The command of the totalitarians was "Thou shalt".
Our command is Thou art No one whom we bring to this place ever stands out against us.
Everyone is washed clean.
Even those three miserable traitors in whose innocence you once believed— —Jones,
Aaronson and Rutherford— —in the end we broke them down. I took part in their
interrogation myself. I saw them gradually worn down, whimpering groveling weeping—
—and in the end it was not with pain or fear, only with penitence.
By the time we had finished with them there were only the shells of men.
There was nothing left in them except sorrow for what they had done, and love of Big Brother.
It was touching to see how they loved him. They begged to be shot quickly, so
that they could die while their minds were still clean.'
His voice had grown almost dreamy.
The exaltation, the lunatic enthusiasm, was still in his face.
He is not pretending, thought Winston; he is not a hypocrite; he believes every word he says.
What most oppressed him was the consciousness of his own intellectual imperiority
He watched the heavy yet graceful formed strolling to and fro, in and out of the
range of his vision.
O'Brien was a being in always larger than himself.
There was no idea that he had ever had, or could have, that O'Brien had not long
ago known, examined and rejected.
His mind contained Winston's mind.
But in that case how could it be true that O'Brien was mad?
It must be he, Winston, who was mad.
O'Brien haltered and looked down at him.
His voice had grown Stone again foreign Do not imagine that you will save
yourself, Winston, however completely you surrender to us.
No one who has once gone astray has ever spared. And even if we chose to let you
live out the natural term of your life, still you would never escape from us.
What happens to you here is forever Understand that in advance.
We shall crush you down to the point from which there is no coming back.
Things will happen to you from which you could not recover, if you lived a thousand years.
Never again will you be capable of ordinary human feeling. Everything will
be dead inside you. Never again will you be capable of love, or friendship, or joy
of living, or laughter, or curiosity, or courage, or integrity. You will be hollow.
We shall squeeze you empty, and then we shall fill you with ourselves.'
He paused and signed to the man in the white coat.
Winston was aware of some heavy piece of apparatus being pushed into place behind his head.
O'Brien had sat down beside the bed, so that his face was almost on a level with Winston's.
'Three thousand,' he said, speaking of a Winston's head to the man in the white coat.
Two soft pads, which felt slightly moist, clamped themselves against Winston's temples.
He quailed. There was pain coming, a new kind of pain.
O'Brien laid a hand reassuringly, almost kindly, on his.
'This time it will not hurt,' he said. 'Keep your eyes fixed on mine.'
At this moment there was a devastating explosion of what seemed like an
explosion, though it was not certain whether there was any noise. There was
undoubtedly a blinding flash of light.
Winston was not hurt, only prostrated.
Although he had already been lying on his back when the thing happened, he had
a curious feeling that he had been knocked into that position.
A terrific, painless blow had flattened him out. Also something had happened inside his head.
As his eyes regained their focus he remembered who he was, and where he was,
and recognized the face that was gazing into his own; but somewhere or rather
there was a large patch of emptiness, as though a piece had been taken out of his brain.
'It will not last,' said O'Brien looked me in the eyes. What country is Oceania at war with?'
Winston thought.
He knew what was meant by Oceania, and that he himself was a citizen of Oceania.
He also remembered Eurasia and East Asia but who was at war with whom he did not
know. In fact he had not been aware that there was any war.
'I don't remember.'
'Oceania is at war with East Asia Do you remember that now?'
'Yes.'
Oceania has always been at war with East Asia Since the beginning of your life,
since the beginning of the Party, since the beginning of history, the war has
continued without a break, always the same war. Do you remember that?'
'Yes 11 years ago you created a legend about three men who had been condemned to
death for treachery. You pretended that you had seen a piece of paper which
proved them innocent.
No such piece of paper ever existed. You invented it, and later you grew to believe in it.
You remember now the very moment at which you first invented it. Do you remember that?'
'Yes.'
'Just now I held up the fingers of my hand to you. You saw five fingers. Do you
remember that?'
'Yes where Brian held up the fingers of his left hand, with the thumb concealed.
'There are five fingers there. Do you see five fingers?'
'Yes.'
And he did see them, for a fleeting instant, before the scenery of his mind
changed. He saw five fingers, and there was no deformity.
Then everything was normal again, and the old fear, the hatred and the bewilderment
came crowding back again.
But there had been a moment— —he did not know how long 30 seconds, perhaps— —of
luminous certainty, when each new suggestion of her Brands had built up a patch of emptiness and
become absolute truth, and when two and two could have been three as easily as
five, if that were what was needed.
It had faded but before O'Brien had dropped his hand; but though he could not
recapture it, he could remember it, as one remembers a vivid experience at some
period of one's life when one was in effect a different person.
'You see now,' said O'Brien, 'that it is at any rate possible.'
'Yes,' said Winston.
O'Brien stood up with a satisfied heir Over to his left Winston saw the man in
the white coat break an ample and draw back the plunger of a syringe.
O'Brien turned to Winston with a smile.
In almost the old manner he resettled his spectacles on his nose.
'Do you remember writing in your diary,' he said, 'that it did not matter whether I
was a friend or an enemy, since I was at least a person who understood you and
could be talked to?
You were right. I enjoyed talking to you.
Your mind appeals to me. It resembles my own mind except that you happen to be insane.
Before we bring the session to an end you can ask me a few questions, if you choose.'
'Any question I like?'
'Anything.'
He saw that Winston's eyes were upon the dial. 'It is switched off.
What is your first question?'
'What have you done with Julia?' said Winston.
O'Brien smiled again.
'She betrayed you, Winston. Immediately— —unreservedly. I have seldom seen anyone
come over to us so promptly.
You would hardly recognize her if you saw her. All her rebelliousness, her
deceit, her folly, her dirty-mindedness— —everything has been burned out of her. It
was a perfect conversion, a textbook case.'
'You tortured her?'
O'Brien left this unanswered. 'Next question,' he said.
'Does Big Brother exist?'
'Of course he exists. The Party exists. Big Brother is the embodiment of the Party.'
'Does he exist in the same way as I exist?'
'You do not exist,' said O'Brien.
Once again the sense of helplessness assailed him.
He knew, or he could imagine, the arguments which proved his own
non-existence but they were nonsense, they were only a play on words.
Did not the statement, 'You do not exist', contain a logical absurdity?
But what use was it to say so? His mind shriveled as he thought of the
unanswerable, mad arguments with which O'Brien would demolish him.
'I think I exist,' he said wearily. 'I am conscious of my own identity. I was born,
and I shall die. I have arms and legs. I occupy a particular point in space. No
other solid object can occupy the same point simultaneously.
In that sense, does Big Brother exist?'
'It is of no importance. He exists.'
'Will Big Brother ever die?'
'Of course not. How could he die? Next question.'
'Does the Brotherhood exist?'
'That, Winston, you will never know. If we choose to set you free when we are
finished with you, and if you live to be 90 years old, still you will never learn
whether the answer to that question is Yes or No. As long as you leave it will
be an unsolved riddle in your mind.'
Winston lay silent. His breast rose and fell a little faster.
He still had not asked the question that had come into his mind the first. He had
got to ask it, and yet it was as though his tongue would not utter it.
There was a trace of amusement in O'Brien's face.
Even his spectacles seemed to wear an ironical gleam.
He knows, thought Winston suddenly, he knows what I am going to ask! At the
thoughts the words burst out of him: 'What is in Room 101?'
The expression on O'Brien's face did not change. He answered dryly
You know what is in Room 101, Winston.
Everyone knows what is in Room 101.'. He raised a finger to the man in the white
coat. Evidently the session was at an end.
A needle jerked into Winston's arm. He sank almost instantly into deep sleep